Finding Aid for University Musical Society (University of Michigan) records, 1879-2009.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
University Musical Society (University of Michigan) Records 1879-2009
University of Michigan. University Musical Society.
87378 BImu, Bimu N1 / 2, Bimul N1
Organized in 1879 to "cultivate the public taste for music," the Society sponsors concert series, opera, dance and theater performances at the University of Michigan. The records consist of director’s files of Albert A. Stanley, Charles A. Sink, Gail Rector, and Kenneth Fischer; include correspondence relating to performances and management of the Society; ledgers and account books, board of directors minutes and packets; files concerning the Choral Union, the University of Michigan School of Music, the Henry S. Frieze Memorial Organ Fund, and Hill Auditorium; also visual materials and audiotapes of Board meetings.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
128 linear feet
9 oversize volumes
2 oversize folders
Material from the UMS (donor 2996 ) was first received in 1953. Accessions are received periodically.
The records are open for research use with the exception of recent exclusive officers files and contracts. Closed files are located in:
Executive Officers Records -- Boxes 121-123, 128
Contracts -- Boxes 124-127 (Closed - Records Center Storage)
The University Musical Society was organized in 1879 by members of the university faculty called together by University President Henry S. Frieze. In 1881 it was incorporated as a nonprofit educational corporation. The society twice extended its corporate existence. In 1969 it was reincorporated "in perpetuity."
The society states that its purpose is to, in part, "cultivate the public taste for music and afford opportunities for the acquisition of musical knowledge and skill..." Affiliated with it, but technically governed by separate boards, were the Choral Union, the University Orchestra and the Ann Arbor School of Music. Despite their technical independence, in reality interlocking directorships led to a situation in which members of the UMS Board of Directors administered the various subordinate units.
In 1892 this situation was formally recognized. The independent governing boards of the Choral Union, Orchestra, and School of Music were disbanded and all three institutions came directly under the jurisdiction of the UMS directors. The school's name was changed to the University School of Music, and funds were raised for the construction of a building for the school.
The Choral Union itself was an outgrowth of the Messiah Club and consisted of singers from several Ann Arbor churches as well as the university community. This organization has continued its traditional Messiah performances as well as participation in May Festival concerts.
In 1893 it was proposed that the society's concert series close with a festival of three concerts rather than with a single event as had been the custom. The three-day event was a great success and, in 1894, the May Festival became an annual occurrence.
While always closely associated with the university, the UMS was and remains technically independent from the control of the Board of Regents. Generally satisfactory, this situation proved troublesome regarding musical education. In 1905 the Regents authorized Michigan students to perform accredited studies at the UMS-governed University School of Music. In 1929 the regents and UMS agreed that the University School of Music should become a component part of the University of Michigan, however the school would continue to be administratively under the control of the UMS Board of Directors whose decisions would be subject to the approval of the regents.
In 1940 the University Musical Society relinquished all rights and responsibilities regarding the School of Music to the regents of the University of Michigan who agreed to assume full responsibility for the school's operation. This separation was both legal and physical as the society left its offices in the School of Music to occupy offices on the first floor of Burton Memorial Tower.
The Choral Union Series, begun in 1889, has served as the major series of concerts presented by the UMS. Presentations have included major orchestras and artists from around the world. The Philadelphia Orchestra began a tenure with the May Festival in 1936, an association which lasted until 1984. Interest in presenting an expanded base of concerts led to the establishment of the Chamber Arts Series in 1963 which focused on chamber music. A Summer Concert Series took place from 1964 to 1971.
In 1960 the University Musical Society recommended changes to Hill Auditorium to allow for an orchestra pit and proscenium which would make possible the introduction of ethnic folk dance, ballet and opera presentations as well. These performances also took place in Rackham Auditorium and, beginning in 1971, the Power Center for the Performing Arts.
In addition to the above series, the University Musical Society also sponsors special (non-subscription) concerts. Among these have been special recitals by Arthur Rubenstein, Marian Anderson, and Vladimir Horowitz. The University Musical Society and School of Music have also sponsored benefit concerts for the School of Music featuring artists of international repute with the University Symphony. Many world premieres of choral and orchestral works have been commissioned by the University Musical Society and performed by the Choral Union.
In the 1980s and 1990s the University Musical Society faced the challenge of the increasing costs of performances and of the need to raise a considerable portion of the operating budget through gifts. The latter led to an expansion in the development efforts of the staff. There was also a perceived need to offer a more varied choice of performances in order to attract patrons of all ages and musical taste. The work space occupied by the UMS, Burton Tower, and Hill Auditorium, its major venue, were both in need of renovation. Changes and activities documented in the 1990-1998 accession include the demise of the May Festival and the beginning of the Distinguished Artist Award--the last May Festival took place in 1995; the Distinguished Artist Award was first awarded in May 1996--and the development of a renovation plan for Hill Auditorium. The plan was approved by the Regents in September 1990 and fund raising began as part of the university's Capital Campaign.
Presidents of the University Musical Society
1879-1881 Henry S. Frieze
1881-1883 Alexander Winchell
1883-1889 Henry S. Frieze
1889-1891 Alexander Winchell
1891-1927 Francis W. Kelsey
1927-1968 Charles A. Sink
1968-1987 Gail W. Rector
Executive Directors of the University Musical Society
1987- Kenneth Fischer
The records of the University Musical Society document its founding in 1879, governance and administrative restructuring through the years, its activities sponsoring musical, dance and theatrical performances on campus, and its role in music and arts education. The records include directors' correspondence files, board of directors minutes, ledgers and financial records, photographs, sound recordings and videotapes.
Intellectually, the records are organized into eight series: Directors' Correspondence, Financial records, Historical file, Board of Directors, Committees, Topical File, Contracts, Photographs, President's Correspondence, Staff Files, Executive Directors' Files, and Motion Pictures (film, videotape and dvd).
The records were received in several major and numerous small accessions and the physical arrangement of the records (the order in which they are arranged in boxes/folders) reflects this. In this finding aid, the records are described in term of their intellectual organization regardless of the particular accession in which they were received. As a result, the box number order in which the descriptions are displayed in the contents list will not always be consecutive.
Subjects:
Henry S. Frieze Memorial Organ Fund (University of Michigan); Hill Auditorium (University of Michigan); Music--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Choral Union.; University of Michigan--Choral organizations.; University of Michigan. School of Music.; University of Michigan. University Musical Society.; Ann Arbor May Festival.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor May Festival.; Fairlane (Dearborn, Mich.); Hill Auditorium (University of Michigan); Music--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Musicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Photographs.; Videotapes.; Revelli, William D. (William Donald), 1902-1994.; Sink, Alva Joanna Gordon.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. University Musical Society.; Royal Shakespeare Company.; Norman, Jessye.; Rushdie, Salman.; Williams, Ralph G.
Contributors:
Fischer, Kenneth M.; Rector, Gail Wesley, 1918-; Sink, Charles A. (Charles Albert), 1879-1972.; Stanley, Albert A. (Albert Augustus), 1851-1932.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Motion pictures.; Videotapes.
- Director's Correspondence 1893-1983
  The series Director's Correspondence, 1898 to 1983 (boxes 1-64, 68-98, 103-106) is by far the largest in the collection and probably provides the greatest research interest. The correspondence covers the tenures of directors Francis W. Kelsey, Charles A. Sink and Gail W. Rector. The Directors' Correspondence series is organized by year and thereunder alphabetically by correspondent. There are occasional exceptions to this, for example, correspondence with or related to the National Association of Concert Managers, 1956-1962, is all filed under 1956 (box 79). This file reflects Charles Sink's important role within that organization.
  Certain portions of the correspondence from the Rector years have been sampled, among these are correspondence from contributors, thank you notes from school groups and others receiving complimentary tickets, complaints, and "fan" letters. The large volume of inquiries received annually by Mr. Rector from both agents and performing artists interested in participating in a UMS concert series have not been retained.
  Prior to 1941, correspondence regarding the School of Music is also found in this series. In general, however, the early correspondence is of low research value, serving the UMS as a general office file and containing great quantities of routine information about ticket purchases and other predictable concerns.
  This series contains correspondence relating to events sponsored under the auspices of the University Musical Society. When attempting to locate artist correspondence in this series, it is recommended that the researcher look under both the artist and agent names. The greater bulk of correspondence with regard to individual artists is handled through the agent, rather than the artist themselves. There are, however, exceptions to this rule.
  The Philadelphia Orchestra and May Festival folders contain a large amount of correspondence from conductor Eugene Ormandy, often providing insights into his ideas regarding programming and interpretation of specific works. Correspondence of other May Festival participants can also be found in various May Festival folders. A number of letters from composer Aaron Copland are included in the 1976 folders. He conducted several of his works in that year's May Festival.
  Many artists of outstanding international repute are also represented in this series. Vladimir Horowitz gave several performances for the UMS and his correspondence is located in the folders of his agent, Harold Shaw, for the years 1976 and 1978. A list of Horowitz's personal requests for a performance is included, as is correspondence with his wife, Wanda Toscanini Horowitz, who discusses the presentation of a film honoring her father that was to be presented in conjunction with a performance of her husband.
  In 1981 Alberto Ginastera was commissioned to write a piano concerto to be premiered by Anthony di Bonaventura at a UMS concert. Correspondence related to this event is located in the Thea Dispeker Artists folder. The 1982 Ann Arbor Summer Festival folder includes transcripts of two interviews Gail Rector conducted with French mime Marcel Marceau.
  A large number of artists are represented in the 1983 and 1984 Gail Rector 25th anniversary folders. These are indicative of the relationships Rector established with these artists during his tenure with the University Musical Society.
  Probably some of the more surprising correspondence in this collection are a series of letters from Dr. Jack Kevorkian in 1976 and 1977. He was involved in the production of a video of UMS Messiah performances.
  As stated above, this collection does not attempt to represent the hundreds of inquiries for performance received by Mr. Rector. However, evidence of the scope of these inquiries can be found in many of the agent folders.
  - 1898-1901
    - A-O (Box 1)
    - P-Z (Box 2)
  - 1902-1907
    - A-G (Box 2)
    - H-Z (Box 3)
  - 1908-1910 (Box 4)
    - A-S (Box 4)
    - T-Z (Box 5)
  - 1911-1912
    - A-H (Box 5)
    - I-Z (Box 6)
  - 1913 (Box 7)
    - A-V (Box 7)
    - W-Z (Box 8)
  - 1914
    - A-R (Box 8)
    - S-Z (Box 9)
  - 1915
    - A-J (Box 9)
    - K-Z (Box 10)
  - 1916-1918 (Box 11)
    - A-E (Box 11)
    - F-L (Box 12)
    - M-S (Box 13)
    - T-Z (Box 14)
  - 1919-1921
    - A-B (Box 14)
    - C-H (Box 15)
    - I-Q (Box 16)
    - R-Z (Box 17)
  - 1922 (Box 18)
    - A-R (Box 18)
    - S-Z (Box 19)
  - 1923
    - A-J (Box 19)
    - K-Z (Box 20)
  - 1924
    - A-B (Box 20)
    - C-M (Box 21)
    - N-Z (Box 22)
  - 1925
    - A-C (Box 22)
    - D-Q (Box 23)
    - R-Z (Box 24)
  - 1926
    - A-D (Box 24)
    - E-Q (Box 25)
    - R-Z (Box 26)
  - 1927
    - A-B (Box 26)
    - C-M (Box 27)
    - N-Z (Box 28)
  - 1928
    - A-C (Box 28)
    - D-O (Box 29)
    - P-Z (Box 30)
  - 1929
    - A (Box 30)
    - B-H (Box 31)
    - I-S (Box 32)
    - T-Z (Box 33)
  - 1930
    - A-D (Box 33)
    - E-N (Box 34)
    - O-Z (Box 35)
  - 1931
    - A (Box 35)
    - B-I (Box 36)
    - J-Q (Box 37)
    - R-Z (Box 38)
  - 1932
    - A (Box 38)
    - B-J (Box 39)
    - K-U (Box 40)
    - V-Z (Box 41)
  - 1933
    - A-F (Box 41)
    - G-R (Box 42)
    - S-Z (Box 43)
  - 1934
    - A-C (Box 43)
    - D-M (Box 44)
    - N-Z (Box 45)
  - 1935
    - A (Box 45)
    - B-J (Box 46)
    - K-S (Box 47)
    - T-Z (Box 48)
  - 1936
    - A-C (Box 48)
    - D-M (Box 49)
    - N-V (Box 50)
    - W-Z (Box 51)
  - 1937
    - A-F (Box 51)
    - G-O (Box 52)
    - P-Z (Box 53)
  - 1938 (Box 54)
    - A-F (Box 54)
    - G-N (Box 55)
    - O-V (Box 56)
    - W-Z (Box 57)
  - 1939
    - A-H (Box 57)
    - I-V (Box 58)
    - W-Z (Box 59)
  - 1939-1940
    - A-N (Box 59)
    - O-Z (Box 60)
  - 1940
    - A-L (Box 60)
    - M-Z (Box 61)
  - 1941
    - A-F (Box 61)
    - G-Z (Box 62)
  - 1942
    - A-C (Box 62)
    - D-Z (Box 63)
  - 1943
    - A-Z (Box 64)
  - 1944 (Box 68)
    - A-Z (Box 68)
  - 1945
    - A-G (Box 68)
    - H-Z (Box 69)
  - 1946
    - A-N (Box 69)
    - O-Z (Box 70)
  - 1947
    - A-Q (Box 70)
    - R-Z (Box 71)
  - 1948
    - A-Q (Box 71)
    - R-Z (Box 72)
  - 1949
    - A-Z (Box 72)
  - 1950 (Box 73)
    - A-Z (Box 73)
  - 1951 (Box 74)
    - A-Z (Box 74)
  - 1952
    - A-B (Box 74)
    - C-Z (Box 75)
  - 1953
    - A-C (Box 75)
    - D-Z (Box 76)
  - 1954
    - A-H (Box 76)
    - I-Z (Box 77)
  - 1955
    - A-L (Box 77)
    - M-Z (Box 78)
  - 1956
    - A-O (Box 78)
    - P-Z (Box 79)
  - National Association of Concert Managers 1956-1962 (Box 79)
  - 1957
    - A-Z (Box 80)
  - 1958
    - A-Z (Box 81)
  - 1959
    - A-C (Box 81)
    - C-Z (Box 82)
    - H-Z (Box 83)
  - 1961
    - A-T (Box 83)
    - T-Z (Box 84)
  - 1962
    - A-Z and UMS form correspondence 1958-1962 (Box 84)
  - 1963
    - A-Z (Box 85)
  - 1964
    - A (Box 85)
    - A-Z (Box 86)
  - 1965
    - A-Z (Box 87)
  - 1966
    - A (Box 87)
    - A-Z (Box 88)
  - 1967
    - A-U (Box 89)
    - V-Z (Box 90)
  - 1968
    - A-S (Box 90)
    - T-Z (Box 91)
  - 1969
    - A-M (Box 91)
    - M-Z (Box 92)
  - 1970
    - A-Z (Box 92)
  - 1971
    - A-Z (Box 93)
  - 1972
    - A-C (Box 93)
    - C-Z (Box 94)
  - 1973
    - A-K (Box 95)
    - L-Z (Box 96)
  - 1974
    - A-I (Box 96)
    - I-Z (Box 97)
  - 1975
    - A-C (Box 97)
    - D-Z (Box 98)
  - 1976
    - A (Box 103)
    - Advisory Board (Box 103)
    - Anders (Mariedi) Management (Box 103)
    - B (Box 103)
    - Baltimore Symphony Orchestra (Box 103)
    - Barrett (Herbert) Management (Box 103)
    - Beall (Harry) Management (Box 103)
    - Beacon Concerts, Ltd. (Box 103)
    - C (Box 103)
    - Choral Union (Box 103)
    - Columbia Artists Management, Inc. (Box 103)
    - Contributors (Box 103)
    - D (Box 103)
    - Detroit Symphony Orchestra (Box 103)
    - Development Office (Box 103)
    - Dispeker (Thea) Artists' Representative (Box 103)
    - E (Box 103)
    - F (Box 103)
    - Festival Chorus/European Tour, 2 folders (Box 103)
    - G (Box 103)
    - H (Box 103)
    - Hillyer (Kazuko) International Inc. (Box 103)
    - Hurok Concerts Inc. (Box 103)
    - I (Box 103)
    - Interlochen Arts Academy (Box 103)
    - International Society of Performing Arts Administrators (Box 103)
    - J (Box 103)
    - K (Box 103)
    - L (Box 103)
    - M (Box 103)
    - May Festival (Box 103)
    - Messiah (Box 103)
    - N (Box 103)
    - P (Box 103)
    - Patrons (Box 103)
    - Philadelphia Orchestra (Box 103)
    - R (Box 103)
    - Rohan, Jindrich (Box 103)
    - S (Box 103)
    - Soffer (Sheldon) Management Inc. (Box 103)
    - Shaw Concerts, Inc. (Box 103)
    - T (Box 103)
    - Tubingen, Germany (Box 103)
    - University of Michigan
      - Intra-University (Box 103)
      - Scheduling Office (Box 103)
      - School of Music (Box 103)
    - V (Box 103)
    - W (Box 103)
    - X,Y,Z (Box 103)
  - 1977
    - A (Box 103)
    - Association of College, University, and Community Arts Administrators (ACUCAA) (Box 103)
    - Anders (Mariedi) Management (Box 103)
    - B (Box 103)
    - Barrett (Herbert) Management (Box 103)
    - Beall (Harry) Management (Box 103)
    - Big Ten Concert Managers (Box 103)
    - Breslin (Herbert) Management (Box 103)
    - C (Box 103)
    - Choral Union (Box 103)
    - Colbert Artists Management (Box 103)
    - Columbia Artists Management, Inc. (Box 103)
    - Complaints (Box 104)
    - Contributors (Box 104)
    - D (Box 104)
    - Development (Box 104)
    - Dispeker (Thea) Management (Box 104)
    - Fan Letters (Box 104)
    - Festival Chorus (Box 104)
    - G (Box 104)
    - H (Box 104)
    - Hillyer (Kazuko) Management (Box 104)
    - Hurok Concerts Inc. (Box 104)
    - I (Box 104)
    - Interlochen Arts Academy (Box 104)
    - International Society of Performing Arts Administrators (ISPAA) (Box 104)
    - J (Box 104)
    - K (Box 104)
    - L (Box 104)
    - M (Box 104)
    - May Festival (Box 104)
    - N (Box 104)
    - P (Box 104)
    - Philadelphia Orchestra (Box 104)
    - Q (Box 104)
    - R (Box 104)
    - Rohan, Jindrich (Box 104)
    - S (Box 104)
    - Shaw Concerts, Inc. (Box 104)
    - T (Box 104)
    - University of Michigan
      - Intra-University (Box 104)
      - Scheduling Office (Box 104)
      - School of Music (Box 104)
    - V,W (Box 104)
  - 1978
    - A (Box 104)
    - Association of College, University, and Community Arts Administrators (ACUCAA) (Box 104)
    - Anders (Mariedi) Artists Management (Box 104)
    - B (Box 104)
    - Barrett (Herbert) Management (Box 104)
    - Beall (Harry) Management (Box 104)
    - Big Ten Concert Managers (Box 104)
    - Breslin (Herbert) Inc. (Box 104)
    - C (Box 104)
    - Choral Union
      - Ticket Policy (Box 104)
    - Columbia Artists Management, Inc. (Box 104)
    - Complaints (Box 104)
    - Contributors (Box 104)
    - D (Box 104)
    - Dispeker (Thea) Artists Management (Box 104)
    - E (Box 104)
    - F (Box 104)
    - Festival Chorus (Box 104)
    - G (Box 104)
    - H (Box 104)
    - Hillyer (Kazuko) Management (Box 104)
    - ICM Artists Ltd. (Box 104)
    - Interlochen Arts Academy (Box 104)
    - International Society of Performing Arts Administrators (ISPAA) (Box 104)
    - J (Box 104)
    - K (Box 104)
    - L (Box 104)
    - M (Box 104)
    - May Festival (Box 104)
    - N (Box 104)
    - P (Box 104)
    - Philadelphia Orchestra (Box 104)
    - Q (Box 104)
    - R (Box 104)
    - Russian Tour (Box 104)
    - S (Box 104)
    - Shaw Concerts Inc.
      - General (Box 104)
      - Horowitz, Vladimir (Box 104)
    - T (Box 104)
    - University of Michigan
      - Intra-University (Box 104)
      - Scheduling Office (Box 104)
      - School of Music (Box 104)
    - V,W (Box 104)
    - White House Visit (Box 104)
    - X,Y,Z (Box 104)
  - 1979
    - A (Box 104)
    - Anders (Mariedi) Artists Management (Box 104)
    - Association of College, University, and Community Arts Administrators (ACUCAA) (Box 104)
    - B (Box 104)
    - Barrett (Herbert) Management (Box 104)
    - Beall (Harry) Management (Box 104)
    - Big Ten Concert Managers (Box 104)
    - Breslin (Herbert) Inc. (Box 104)
    - C (Box 104)
    - Choral Union (Box 104)
    - Colbert Artists Management Inc. (Box 104)
    - Columbia Artists Management Inc. (Box 105)
    - Complaints (Box 105)
    - Contributors (Box 105)
    - D (Box 105)
    - Dispeker (Thea) Artists Management (Box 105)
    - E,F (Box 105)
    - Fan Letters (Box 105)
    - Festival Chorus
      - Egyptian Trip (Box 105)
      - General (Box 105)
    - G (Box 105)
    - H (Box 105)
    - Hillyer (Kazuko) Management (Box 105)
    - ICM Artists Ltd. (Box 105)
    - Interlochen Arts Academy (Box 105)
    - International Society of Performing Arts Administrators (ISPAA) (Box 105)
    - J (Box 105)
    - K (Box 105)
    - L (Box 105)
    - M (Box 105)
    - May Festival (Box 105)
    - N (Box 105)
    - P (Box 105)
    - Philadelphia Orchestra (Box 105)
    - R (Box 105)
    - S (Box 105)
    - Shaw Concerts Inc. (Box 105)
    - T (Box 105)
    - Testimonials (100th Anniversary) (Box 105)
    - U (Box 105)
    - University of Michigan
      - Intra-University (Box 105)
      - Scheduling Office (Box 105)
      - School of Music (Box 105)
    - V,W (Box 105)
  - 1980
    - A (Box 105)
    - Anders (Mariedi) Artists Management (Box 105)
    - Ann Arbor Summer Festival (Box 105)
    - B (Box 105)
    - Barrett (Herbert) Management (Box 105)
    - Beall (Harry) Management (Box 105)
    - Big Ten Concert Managers (Box 105)
    - C (Box 105)
    - Columbia Artists Management Inc. (Box 105)
    - China/Japan Tour (Box 105)
    - Choral Union (Box 105)
    - Complaints (Box 105)
    - Contributors (Box 105)
    - D (Box 105)
    - Dispeker (Thea) Artists Representative (Box 105)
    - E (Box 105)
    - F (Box 105)
    - Festival Chorus (Box 105)
    - G (Box 105)
    - H (Box 105)
    - Hillyer (Kazuko) Management (Box 105)
    - I (Box 105)
    - ICM Artists Ltd. (Box 105)
    - International Society of Performing Arts Administrators (ISPAA) (Box 105)
    - J (Box 105)
    - K (Box 105)
    - L (Box 105)
    - M (Box 105)
    - May Festival (Box 105)
    - N (Box 105)
    - P (Box 105)
    - Philadelphia Orchestra (Box 105)
    - R (Box 105)
    - S (Box 105)
    - Shaw Concerts Inc. (Box 105)
    - T (Box 105)
    - University of Michigan
      - Intra-University (Box 105)
      - Scheduling Office (Box 105)
      - School of Music (Box 105)
    - V,W,Y (Box 105)
  - 1981
    - A (Box 105)
    - Associations of College, University, and Community Arts Administrators (ACUCAA) (Box 105)
    - B (Box 105)
    - Barrett (Herbert) Management (Box 105)
    - Beall (Harry) Management (Box 105)
    - Big Ten Concert Managers (Box 105)
    - C (Box 105)
    - Choral Union (Box 105)
    - Columbia Artists Management Inc. (Box 105)
    - Complaints (Box 105)
    - Contributors (Box 105)
    - D (Box 105)
    - Development (Box 105)